Finding Aid for Alan E. Abrams Papers 1959-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alan E. Abrams papers 1959-1982, 1964-1971
Abrams, Alan E.
2 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
Alan Abrams is a Detroit-based press agent/public relations consultant in the music business; publicist for Motown Record Corporation, 1964-1966, later with Stax Records, 1967-1968. The collection consists of press releases, clippings, publicity material, scrapbooks containing press coverage of the recording artists that he represented, including the Supremes, photographs, and his writings about Motown, Otis Redding, and Florence Ballard.
9943 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was acquired from Mr. Abrams in 1998 and 2011. Donor no. 8763
The collection is open for research.
Al Abrams was a press agent/public relations consultant for Motown records during its early formative period, roughly 1964 to 1966. In 1959, having worked as a trainee in the mailroom of Detroit's McCann-Erickson Advertising Agency, Abrams signed on as the first employee of Berry Gordy's Rayber Music Writing and Recording Company. Abrams, though a young man at the time, here began developing skills needed to be a publicist within the music business. He knew that for a record to succeed it must be played on the radio. Abrams got to know all of the important Detroit area DJs and participated in publicity stunts to make known artists and their records.
Abrams stayed with Rayber for a time then left to follow other opportunities. In 1964, he returned to Gordy and his Motown company which was still a small struggling firm. He stayed with Motown for two years handling the press relations first for singer Mary Wells then for the Supremes. During this period, Motown and its stable of singers and musical groups, such as the Supremes, began its string of great successes. In 1966 Abrams left Motown to form his own public relations firm - Al Abrams Associates - where he worked as public relations consultant for the Stax Record Company, a Memphis-based firm, and Stax-Volt recording artists such as Otis Redding. Following Redding's tragic death, Abrams ended his association with Stax-Volt in 1968 to work independently. Florence Ballard who had left the Supremes and was no longer working for Motown became his biggest client. He also did press work for Invictus Records based in Detroit and worked with James Brown, Aretha Franklin, and many other artists.
The Al Abrams collection contains scrapbooks, correspondence, press releases, photographs, and memoirs detailing Abrams' work as a publicist and press agent for Detroit's Motown and for Stax Records in Memphis. The collection is valuable for its documentation of Motown in the period of the early to mid-1960s when this Detroit company was beginning its great string of record successes. Abrams was a great collector of press and other materials about the artists who worked for Motown and Stax-Volt.
The Abrams collection measures two linear feet and four oversize volumes whose contents have been foldered. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Motown Record Company, Stax Record Company, Al Abrams Associates, Miscellaneous, Visual Materials, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Abrams, Alan E.; Ballard, Florence, 1943-1976.; Singers--United States.; Motown Record Corporation.; Performing arts--Public relations.; Press agents.; Redding, Otis, 1941-1967.; Stax Records.; Rhythm and blues music.; Supremes (Musical group); Sound recording industry.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Abrams, Alan E.; Ballard, Florence, 1943-1976.; Beatles.; Cambridge, Godfrey, 1933-1976.; Cavanaugh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.; Dave Clark Five (Musical group); Disc jockeys--Michigan--Detroit.; Epstein, Brian, 1934-1967.; Gaye, Marvin.; Good, Tommy.; Gordy, Berry.; Gordy, Berry, 1888-1978.; Motown Record Corporation.; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.; Publicity.; Silvers, Phil, 1911-1985.; Sound recording industry.; Stax Records.; Supremes (Musical group); Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Velvet Underground (Musical group); Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Wonder, Stevie.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videocassettes.
- Motown Record Company
  The Motown Record Company series consists of a draft of part of a proposed memoir of Abrams dealing with his association with Motown, its founder Berry Gordy, Jr. and its biggest musical group, the Supremes. This series also includes an extensive collection of the press releases from the company in the period of 1964-1966.
  - "Motown Memoirs" 1970, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (draft of proposed chapter intended as a memoir of Abrams experiences with Motown)
  - Press releases undated, 1964-1966, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings and articles (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Stax Record Company
  The Stax Record Company series consists of press releases, promotion material for the company, and a remembrance of Otis Redding following his death in 1968.
  - Press releases 1967 (Box 1)
  - Publicity material for Stax artists (Box 1)
  - Recollection of Otis Redding 1968 (Box 1)
- Al Abrams Associates
  The Al Abrams Associates series mainly documents press coverage of Florence Ballard and other mainly Detroit-based artists. There is also some mention here of the proposed "soul bowl" promotion being headed by the Rev. C. L. Franklin.
  - Press releases (Florence Ballard and other clients) 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Florence Ballard law suit 1970 (Box 1)
  - Florence Ballard (articles and draft of article about) 1968 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is arranged alphabetically and consists of files arranged by topic or type of material. Included is Abrams correspondence with members of the press, especially those who wrote about music and the entertainment industry. Most of the letters are brief and chatty in content. Included are notes from Walter Winchell and Bob Talbert.
  - Alan, Lee (anonymous letter charging this radio personality with accepting "payola") (Box 1)
  - "All got rhythm" (start of Abrams novel about the music business) (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence undated, 1959-1971, 1982, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Holland-Dozier-Holland litigation 1968 (Box 1)
  - Invictus Records press materials (Box 1)
  - Invictus Records litigation 1971 (Box 1)
  - New Worlds Unlimited publicity proposal December 1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes photographs and one videocassette. The photographs include publicity photos and candid shots of the Supremes, Marvin Gaye, Stevie Wonder, Tommy Good, and other Motown acts; photos of Berry Gordy and his family; former Supreme Florence Ballard during her solo career; a small number of photos of Stax artists; and promotional stunts performed by Abrams with Detroit radio personalities to publicize new recordings. Some of the photos depict other celebrities visiting Motown or the Gordy family, including the Dave Clark Five, Godfrey Cambridge, the Beatles, Drew Pearson, Brian Epstein, Phil Silvers, and others; and the Supremes with Michigan political figures Jerome Cavanaugh, George Romney, and G. Mennen Williams. One folder of photographs (and one scrapbook folder) documents the Carnaby Street Fun Festival and "The World's First Mod Wedding," promoted by Abrams and sponsored by the Borman Brothers' Food Fair stores. The event took place at the Michigan State Fairgrounds, Nov. 20, 1966, and featured Andy Warhol (painting paper dresses), Gerard Malanga (performing a whip dance), and music by the Velvet Underground with Lou Reed and Nico. Abrams prepared captions for most of the photos, which are included in a separate folder. The videocassette contains a 1965 tape of Motown acts on a local Detroit-Windsor music program.
  - Abrams captions and notes (Box 1)
  - Al Abrams (Box 1)
  - Al Abrams publicity stunts (Box 1)
  - Florence Ballard (includes Godfrey Cambridge, Greg Morris) (Box 1)
  - Marvin Gaye (Box 1)
  - Berry Gordy and family (includes the Beatles) (Box 1)
  - Tommy Good and " March on Motown" (Box 1)
  - Motown acts miscellaneous (includes Brian Epstein, Phil Silvers, Everly Brothers) (Box 1)
  - Stax-Volt (includes Howard Baker) (Box 1)
  - Supremes (Box 1)
  - Supremes with others (includes Dave Clark Five, Jerome Cavanaugh, George Romney, G. Mennen Williams) (Box 1)
  - Stevie Wonder with others (includes Drew Pearson, Paul Newman, Joanne Woodward, Ruby Dee, Tony Bennett, Peter Noone) (Box 1)
  - "World's First Mod Wedding," November 20, 1966 featuring Andy Warhol, Gerard Malanga, and the Velvet Underground with Lou Reed and Nico (Box 1)
  - Videotape of Robin Seymour "Teen Town" television program featuring Berry Gordy, Jr., the Supremes, the temptations, Stevie Wonder, Smokey Robinson, the Marvelettes, 1965, VHS tape (Box 1)
  - Negatives--Staff Use Only (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series, formerly stored in large loose-leaf volumes, has been taken apart for preservation reasons and placed in folders. The chronological order of the scrapbooks has been largely maintained with many of the pages of the volumes devoted to the careers of the Supremes, Otis Redding, and Florence Ballard. The scrapbooks represent the mass of clippings and articles from newspapers and music magazines - both mainstream and publications aimed at the African-American community - that Abrams accumulated and pasted together in scrapbooks.
  - Motown Record Company
    - 1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1966, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Stax-Volt Records
    - 1967, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - By topic
    - Abrams and miscellaneous clients 1965-1968 (Box 4)
    - Mod wedding 1966 (Box 4)
    - Death of Otis Redding 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Florence Ballard 1968 (Box 4)